Are you thinking of buying your own home?
From selecting a home to
negotiating the price, buying a house is not an easy
task. Let's make it a little easier for you.
In this video, I will tell you five
important things that you must keep in
mind before buying your first home
and will also give you a checklist which will help you in
buying a home. So let's get
started. Decide on your budget
and stick to it. First and foremost, do
not go out to buy a house without a budget.
We can divide budgeting into two important paths. The
first part is margin money, that is,
all those big ticket expenses which
you may have to pay from your own resources.
And the second is the affordability of your home loan.
Lenders can give a maximum loan of only
70 to 90% of the property based on your income. This
means that
you will have to make a down payment of the remaining 10 to 30%.
Apart from this, there are many other expenses like
registration, interior decoration. To
cover all these expenses, first of all you
should ensure that you have the funds for your home.  At least
32-40%
margin money should be available on the shortlisted property, i.e., if the house is worth Rs 1 crore, then the
margin money should be Rs 30-40 lakh. Then comes the question of whether you will be able to
comfortably repay the loan amount of your shortlisted house.
To understand this, check that the total of all your loans, i.e.,
new home loan, plus any outstanding
dues on old loans, should
not exceed 40% of your current monthly household income.
That is, if your monthly household income
is Rs 1 lakh, then the total amount of all your loans should be
less than Rs 40,000. But what is the meaning of budgeting
if you cannot implement it? Try
not to stretch your budget too much so that
your new house does not disturb your cash flow and
other important things like children's education and
retirement plans.
Check the builder's track record.
Before making a big investment like buying a house,
you must also check the track record of your shortlisted builder.
How many projects has the builder completed?  Whether the builder has completed or
how many projects are currently underway,
you can find all this information on the RERA site.
You simply need to visit your state's RERA
site and enter the builder's RERA
number. This will
display project details. If you're
using an agent,
you can also enter the builder's registration number on your state's
RERA website to check the project status.
Here, you'll find out
how authorized the builder and agent are.
Another important
question is whether you should
buy an under-construction property or a ready-to-move-in property. An
under-construction property may be available at a slightly lower price,
but
during construction, you may have to bear the cost of both home loan interest and current home expenses.
Therefore, ready-to-
move-in may be a better option
because you won't have to wait for your home to be built. You won't have to pay the
GST applicable on under-construction flats
and
you'll also receive full income tax benefits. However, the
overall price of ready-to-move-in properties may be higher than that of under-construction properties. So,
if you're considering
investing in an under-construction property, consider buying a ready-to-move-in property.  If you're
considering this,
make the payment according to the Construction Linked Payment Plan.
In this, the lender disburses the loan amount to the builder based on the
stage of construction completion.
You'll have to pay the same amount as the lender pays to the builder. This will keep
your expenses under control
and
your EMI won't increase if the project is delayed.
Checking Documents: Now let's talk
about some important documents you should
definitely check on any homebuyer.
Before buying a home from any builder,
check the building plan and layout approval. The
builder must obtain plan approval before starting construction.
Next,
check the Land U Certificate. This will help
you determine if the builder is constructing a residential project
in a commercial area or agricultural land. Next,
you need to check the occupancy certificate.
This will tell you whether basic
immunities like electricity, water, and
drainage are available.
Next, you need to check whether there are
any encumbrances on the property.  If
you are
buying an under-construction property,
you should also check the Certificate of Commitment.
This is basically permission for
construction from the local authority. If you are
buying a ready-to-move-in property,
you should also check the Completion Certificate.
You
can also take the help of a lawyer for this due diligence. Lenders also
conduct this due diligence before sanctioning a home loan, but being self-analyzable on these matters can
prove to be very helpful. The
most important document is the one that
transfers ownership of the house from the builder to you.
This document will mention your basic details and
property
immunities. Next, there will be a
payment clause, which will mention the terms of the sale
consideration advice, payment, and balance payment.
These are some basic
details that you should read carefully.
But there are some clauses that should not be there in your sale deed. The
first is the Indemnity Clause.
This clause ensures that there are no liens, taxes, or any other charges
on the property sold to you by the builder.
Apart from this, it should also
state  The property is free
from litigation this month so that no one else can
come and claim the property tomorrow.
Next is the transfer of ownership, which means that the
absolute ownership title is being transferred.
You also need to
check the agreement to see if any conditional clauses have been
inserted. For this, you
can seek the help of a legal expert. Registration
Process: Generally, the sale deed needs to be registered in India. The
buyer has to pay stamp
duty and registration charges. The
percentage of stamp duty
varies from state to state and is typically 4 to
10% of the property value. This deed is
registered in front of 2 witnesses. It is
mandatory to register the property within four months of the sale deed being executed. So, this was a
useful checklist for first-time buyers. Now, are
you wondering about the home loan documentation
checklist? Don't worry, you wo
n't need it because
in a 9C home loan, you don't need 100% paperwork in this
process and up to ₹5 crore.  Home loan can be
easily availed with zero for closure
charges. So download Navya today to get instant home loan.
Link in
description: If you liked this video,
please like and share it and
subscribe to D Nau C YouTube channel for more
such information videos.